每天在職場與家庭中，我們都需要進行關鍵而艱難的對話。我想分享一套快速且高效的四步模型：ROOM 模型。
Recognize（辨識）、Use（運用）、Understand（理解）與 Manage（管理）——這完全關乎情緒智慧。
第一步是辨識（Recognize）：我現在感受如何？對方當下的感受又是什麼？
第二步是運用（Use）：評估情緒對思維與行為的影響。例如，你覺察到自己心生怨懟與防衛，這會導致你在對話中封閉自己；
第三步是理解（Understand）：探究這份情緒背後的成因，以及你希望情緒如何演變。換句話說，對話結束時你希望彼此帶著什麼樣的感受？
第四步是管理（Manage）：思考在對話中需要採取什麼行動來達成理想的情感結果？是創造傾聽的空間，還是保持沉默與同理？
這套 ROOM 技能是高效溝通的基石。我們太常帶著被情緒鉤住的執念或死板技巧進入對話，
但決定對話成敗的真正關鍵，在於我們如何調度自己與對方的情感氛圍。
about what is the cause of this emotion and also how do I want the emotion to
play out over time. In other words, how do I at the end of the conversation want
to be feeling and how do I want the other person to be feeling? And then lastly
is manage. Manage is about thinking what do you need to do in the conversation to
get the emotional outcome that you need? Is it about creating space for
conversation? Is it about listening and being quiet? What is it that is needed in
order to get the outcome? This set of skills, this room model, I think, is
foundational to effective conversations. Too often we go into conversations
thinking about what I want to say in a way that feels really hooked on the
difficulty motion or that's focused on facts and techniques. But what makes
funny effect of conversation is how we manage the emotional tone of the
conversation, both in ourselves and in the other person.